<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to a certain pamphlet written by an vnknowing and vnknown author, vvho takes upon him to answer the true and perfect narrative of the several proceedings concerning the Lord Craven. Published to undeceive those whom that nameless person hath so grosly abused with his falsities, misrecitals, short recitals, and inventions (almost) in every page of his pamphlet.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91657</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867177</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119472</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248509783</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1071_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208207</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867177</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867177e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91657)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1071[3], 249:E1071[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to a certain pamphlet written by an vnknowing and vnknown author, vvho takes upon him to answer the true and perfect narrative of the several proceedings concerning the Lord Craven. Published to undeceive those whom that nameless person hath so grosly abused with his falsities, misrecitals, short recitals, and inventions (almost) in every page of his pamphlet.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 22, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. White,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: The Lord Craven's case, as to the confiscation and sale of his estate by judgment of Parlament.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Craven, William Craven, --  Earl of, 1606-1697.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Lord Craven's case, as to the confiscation and sale of his estate by judgment of Parlament.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Confiscations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119472:1"/>
            <p>A REPLY To a Certain PAMPHLET WRITTEN BY An <hi>Vnknowing</hi> and <hi>Vnknown</hi> Author, VVho takes upon him to answer the True AND PERFECT NARRATIVE OF The Several PROCEEDINGS CONCERNING The Lord Craven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PƲBLISHED</hi> To undeceive those whom that Nameless Person hath so grosly abused with his Falsities, Mis-recitals, short Recitals, and Inventions (almost) in every Page of his <hi>Pamphlet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. White.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119472:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119472:2"/>
            <head>A REPLY To a Certain <hi>PAMPHLET</hi> Written by An <hi>Ʋnknowing</hi> and <hi>Ʋnknown</hi> Author, Who takes upon him to answer the True And Perfect NARRATIVE Of the several PROCEEDINGS CONCERNING The Lord Craven.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Faulconers Examination.</head>
               <opener>Who saith,</opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat about a fortnight before the conclusion of the Treaty at <hi>Breda,</hi> the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Faulconers</hi> Information against the Lord <hi>Craven Feb.</hi> 10. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0</note> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her two Daughters came to <hi>Breda</hi> to the <hi>Scots</hi> King <hi>Charles,</hi> and went not thence till the King went to <hi>Honsleidike,</hi> a house of the Prince of <hi>Oranges.</hi> That during that time, this Informant saw the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> divers times in presence with the said King, and every day with the said King at the Court there, he being there with the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her two Daughters, to take <hi>their leave</hi> (as they said) of the King of <hi>Scots</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:119472:3"/> he went to <hi>Scotland:</hi> That several Officers, about <hi>thirty</hi> in number, made a Petition to the said King, to entertain them to fight for him against the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the recovering of his just Rights, and reinstating him in his Throne, and <hi>deputed</hi> this Informant and Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> to present the said Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who <hi>indeed drew</hi> the same. That when the Informant and some other Officers came to the Court at <hi>Breda,</hi> intending to present the said Petition immediately to the Kings hand, but finding the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> very neer to him, likewise the Marquess of <hi>Newcastle,</hi> who presented his brother Sir <hi>Charles Cavendish</hi> to kiss the said Kings hand the evening before the said Kings departure, who this Informant saw kiss the Kings hand accordingly: the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Cleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Lord <hi>Gerrard, &amp;c.</hi> and a great bustle of business; This Informant, with Colonel <hi>Drury,</hi> applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> intreating him to present the Petition to the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to present it to the King of <hi>Scots:</hi> the said Lord <hi>Craven</hi> taking the Petition, and reading the same Cheerfully, said to Colonel <hi>Drury</hi> and this Informant, <hi>There is the Queen of</hi> Bohemia, <hi>deliver it to her, and I will speak for you:</hi> Upon which they applied themselves to the said Queen, and she presented the Petition: After which the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> the Marquess of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castle,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with some other Lords went into a withdrawing room, where this Informant and company could not enter: But the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> came forth of the withdrawing Chamber, and told this Informant and company, <hi>That they should receive an answer from the Queen of</hi> Bohemia <hi>to their Petition, and that he had spoken to the Queen of</hi> Bohemia <hi>in their behalf,</hi> who afterwards came and told this Informant and company that she had delivered their Petition, and that the King had taken order for it. The <hi>next morning</hi> at three of the Clock the <hi>King departed,</hi> but this Informant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had their Quarters satisfied by the Princess of <hi>Orange,</hi> according to the said Kings order upon their Petition, and thereby to inable them to follow the said King in the prosecution of these Wars against the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> which was the effect of their aforesaid Petition: That this Informant saw the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> very often and familiar with the said King, and enter with the said King into the withdrawing Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and staid there, the last night the said King was at <hi>Breda,</hi> very late.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Richard Faulconer.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:119472:3"/>
               <head>Colonel Hugh Reylys Examination.</head>
               <opener>Who saith,</opener>
               <p>THat during the late Treaty at <hi>Breda,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colonel <hi>Hugh Reyly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> his Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against the Lord <hi>Craven. Feb.</hi> 10. 1650.</note> this Informant did oftentimes see the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> with the now King of <hi>Scots</hi> in his Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, and also walked abroad with him, there being no man more conversant with the King then he. That the said Lord <hi>Craven</hi> during the said Treaty, did twice go to <hi>Rotterdam</hi> and <hi>Dunhagh,</hi> and back again, being imployed, as was commonly <hi>reported</hi> at Court there, by the said King. That the said Lord <hi>Craven</hi> had a charge from the King to look to one Mrs. <hi>Barlow,</hi> who (as is reported, and he believes to be true) had a child by the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> born at <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> which he did: and after the King was gone for <hi>Scotland,</hi> the said Lord <hi>Craven</hi> took the child from her, for which she went to Law with him, and recovered the child back again, <hi>as is reported.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hugh Reyly.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Capt. Kitchingmans Examination.</head>
               <opener>Who saith,</opener>
               <p>THat the said Captain <hi>Thomas Kitchingman</hi> in <hi>April</hi> and <hi>May,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Captain <hi>Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chingmans</hi> Information against the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Feb.</hi> 20. 1650.</note>
                  <hi>1650.</hi> Saw the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> several times with the King of <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Breda,</hi> and wait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng upon the said King several times at his Table at <hi>Breda;</hi> This Informant also saw the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> at the same time with the King of <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Breda,</hi> waiting upon the said King at his Table, and saw the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> many times go into the withdrawing rooms after the said King: This Informant also saw the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> in the Bowling-ally in <hi>Breda</hi> Caste with the said King.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thomas Kitchingman.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>REsolved</hi> by the Parliament that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> is an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der against the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Votes of Confiscation</note> within the <hi>Declaration</hi> of the 24. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1649. Entituled a Declaration of the Commons assembled in Parliament, declaring all Persons who have served the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and have
<pb facs="tcp:119472:4"/> betrayed their trust, or <hi>have</hi> or <hi>shall</hi> adhere to, or aid and assist <hi>Charls Stewart,</hi> Son to the late King, to be Traytors and Rebels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Resolved</hi> by the Parliament that the Estate of the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> be <hi>Confiscated</hi> accordingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Resolved</hi> that the Commissioners for Compounding be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred and required to <hi>Seize</hi> and Sequester all the Estate Real and Personal of the said Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and to <hi>receive</hi> the Rents, Issues and Profits thereof to the <hi>use</hi> of the Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not long since</hi> there was published a true and perfect <hi>Narrative</hi> of the Case of the Right Honourable <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> Baron of <hi>Hampstead</hi> Marshal, whereunto the Author subscribed his name as ready to justifie the same: setting forth the truth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therein, in Parliament at the Council of State, before the Commissioners at <hi>Habberdashers-hall,</hi> and Upper Bench: Serving out the particulars in their own times and colours, without any <hi>Comment</hi> or other <hi>Observation</hi> thereupon: Lest the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er should apprehend the Author intended to byass him in his Judgement, or to lead him in the least manner out of the way of his own reason (the just priviledge of every Reader) which Narrative contains at large the Votes of <hi>Confiscation, Summons,</hi> and all other Votes which at any time passed in Parliament against the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> with exact Copies of every <hi>Petition</hi> presented to the Parliament, by or on the behalf of his Lordship. And lastly, the Remarkable Tryal of <hi>Faulconer</hi> that <hi>Infamous</hi> and <hi>perjured</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is set forth at large in the said <hi>Narrative;</hi> And albeit that <hi>Narrative</hi> was harmlesly penned, and void of offence: Yet hath it received from a Censorious pen (in way of answer thereunto) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch bitter langue: As <hi>Malitious, Scura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lous, False<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Jugling, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining, Partial, Untrue, Unworthy, Unsufferable, Bespattering,</hi> &amp;c. And much more unseemly expressions, fit only for the Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Billingsgate:</hi> The Author (as well he might) being ashamed to put his name to so <hi>Scurrolous</hi> and <hi>Unjustifiable</hi> a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet. It was once Resolved as most prudent to have given no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thereunto, till the unknown Person had appeared to have owned the defence: But not hearing of him, and the Author of the said <hi>Narrative</hi> being desirous to undeceive those whom the unknowing person hath so grosly abused by his <hi>Falsities, Mis-recitals,</hi> short <hi>Recitals,</hi> and <hi>Inventions,</hi> almost in every Page in that Pamphlet: hath thought good to give an Answer to some things which he enforceth as material Objections against the Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> And first,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119472:4"/>
               <head>Concerning the Declaration <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. 1649.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is notoriously known, that the</hi> Lord Craven <hi>was by the late Parliament voted an Offender within the</hi> Declaration <hi>of the</hi> 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>of</hi> August 1649. <hi>and thereupon his Estate confiscated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To convince the nameless Author of his fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity and mistake, in publishing of that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Vote made upon it concerning the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> and for the satisfying of such as are willing to be undeceived; it will be necessary in the first place, to observe the true ground of that Declaration, which was thus; Letters coming to the Council of State from Sir <hi>Charls Coot,</hi> dated at <hi>London-Derry</hi> the 14<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> and 15<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1649. (He being then Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief for the Parliament in the Province of <hi>Ulster</hi>) Mr. <hi>Luke Robinson,</hi> one of that Council, was Ordered to report those Letters to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which he did <hi>Aug.</hi> the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg> 1649. and the same being read in <hi>Parliament,</hi> did inform them of the potency of some Forces under the <hi>Lord Ards</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (who had formerly served the Parliament, but had revolted and declared for the late King against the Parliament▪) In one of which Letters then read in Parliament, Sir <hi>Charls Coot</hi> had this Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage; <hi>That the Parliaments Interest in those Parts was in danger to be wholly lost, and the Forces under his Command likely to be ruined and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed by a numerous Party of</hi> English <hi>and</hi> Scots, <hi>under the conduct of the Lord of</hi> Ards <hi>and other desperate enemies against the Parliament.</hi> After the reading of which Letters, there was much debate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the said Lord of <hi>Ards,</hi> and those <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> under his Conduct, who were formerly in the pay of the Parliament, yet had revolted to the King, and betrayed their trust there, and of the gareat ayd and assistance of <hi>others,</hi> both English and Scots, who were Inhabitants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and not in <hi>pay</hi> of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet adhered to the Enemy; the Parliament (hoping to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119472:5"/> disperse them by publishing a Declaration that they should be proceeded against as Traitors, and their Estates confiscated) thereupon passed this declaratory Vote, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Die Veneris 24. August 1649.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REsolved upon the question by the Commons assembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That this House doth declare, that all persons, whether</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish <hi>or</hi> Scots, <hi>who have been under the</hi> pay <hi>of the Parliament of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>in the service of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and have</hi> revolted <hi>and betrayed their</hi> trust there, <hi>and all other persons who have or shall adhere to, or assist</hi> Charls Stewart, <hi>Son of the late King, or any the forces in</hi> Ireland, <hi>against the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>are, and be adjudged to be Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Rebels to the Commonwealth of</hi> England; <hi>And all their Estates shall be</hi> Confiscated, <hi>and their Persons proceeded against as Traitors, and Rebels; And that all such Officers as have so betrayed their trust be proceeded against by a Court Martial</hi> there.</p>
               <p>Ordered, <hi>That this Declaration be forthwith Printed and Published; And that it be referred to the Council of State to Communicate the same to the Lord Lieutenant of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and such others there, as they shall think fit, that the same may be put in Execution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And those that shall cast their eyes into the Journal Book of that days proceedings in Parliament, may clearly satisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that both that and the other Votes which passed that day, were onely grounded upon those Letters from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and wholly intended for <hi>Ireland;</hi> Where they shall find mention of Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binsons</hi> Report from the Council of State, concerning Sir <hi>Charls Coots</hi> Letters from <hi>Ireland,</hi> with mention of the Articles between General <hi>Owen O Neal,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Richard Coot; With</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solves of the House, that a former Vote of the House of the tenth of this moneth, in the Case of Colonel <hi>Munck</hi> be communicated to Sir <hi>Charls Coot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> the House was well satisfied of the Diligence, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and integrity of Sir <hi>Charls Coot;</hi> with directions for care to be taken for his better supply for the future; That the Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger who brought those Letters should be rewarded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> those severall Letters and Articles, together with the Vote of the House thereupon should be forthwith Printed and Published.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> at the same time the <hi>Declaratory Vote</hi> before mentioned, did pass, entered <hi>only</hi> as a <hi>Resolve</hi> amongst the rest.</p>
               <p>From all which it may be observed,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> That this Declaration was grounded upon those Letters from <hi>Ireland;</hi> Which Letters say that the Parliaments Interest there was in danger to be lost.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it pursued the very words of those Letters, <hi>English,</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119472:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It directeth, that Offenders against it be proceeded against in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That it be Printed and Published, and sent into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the Lord Lieutenant to put the same in Execution <hi>There.</hi> And for that clause, <hi>[And all other persons, &amp;c.]</hi> It is apparent that it had Reference to those other persons, <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> Who were not in pay of the Parliament; Yet did Aid, Assist, and Adhere to the late King and his Forces there in <hi>Ireland</hi> under the Conduct of the Lord of <hi>Ards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Declaration</hi> was never ordered to be published as a Law in <hi>England;</hi> Neither was it ever passed in Parliament as a Law, But meerly a <hi>[Resolve upon the Question]</hi> Nor any <hi>Title</hi> put to it by Vote of Parliament, as is usuall to all Laws made by the Parliament, but onely what Title the <hi>Printer</hi> pleased, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath committed an error; Neither hath he printed it with that <hi>Letter</hi> which all other Laws since the change of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are printed with.</p>
               <p>But the nameless Author <hi>(Page 22.)</hi> conceives he makes an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answerable Objection, when he tells you,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That the Parliament hath resolved, that the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate be Confiscate as an Offender against that Declaration.</p>
               </q>
               <p>If the Parliament, who are Law-makers, without hearing what the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> could say against it; Declare that he is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender within a Declaration of Parliament, which was never Published or Declared to be a Law, and that therefore he shall forfeit his Estate: Who can Controul it but a Parliament? Otherwise, It might have been offered with much reason and modesty (besides what hath been already said as to the ground, end, and aim of that Declaration,) That the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> never served the Parliament in <hi>Ireland, England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland;</hi> Nor ever was in <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor in <hi>England</hi> since the troubles, and so could not betray his trust there; Nor as a private person could ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to, or assist the King or his Forces in <hi>Ireland;</hi> Besides, the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> (and so for nine years together before that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) was out of <hi>England,</hi> and never heard of this Declaration till he was condemned upon it unheard.</p>
               <p>Pag. 22. <hi>He again commits another absurdity concerning the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the</hi> 24. <hi>of</hi> August 1649. <hi>And tells you (that all other persons who have, or shall adhere unto, or assist</hi> Charls Stewart, <hi>Son of the late King, are, and be adjudged Traytors, and Rebels to the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>and their Estates shall be Confiscated; Which (saith this senseless man) meaneth all persons whatsoever, or wheresoever in these Dominions, or beyond the Seas, that have, or shall adhere to</hi> Charls Stewart, <hi>Son of the late King.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119472:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> So that by his making this a distinct qualification within that Declaration, without reference to the clauses pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent or subsequent, which only relate to <hi>Ireland,</hi> or to the Clause of assisting against the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> which he leaves out in his Case; he makes it Treason in any Person <hi>whatsoever,</hi> to assist the Son of the late King <hi>wheresoever</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, whether against <hi>French, Italian, Turk</hi> or <hi>Tartar;</hi> and besides this, he deals most deceitfully with the Reader, For in reciting that clause, (that all other persons, &amp;c. He leaves out after the word (King) this clause (<hi>or any the Forces in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) yet, after that omission goes on confidently with the rest of the Declaration, and saith (and shall be adjudged Traytors, &amp;c.) But it is no marvail if such mistakes happen, when the blind lead the blind: For the Printer first erred in the Title of that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and the nameless Author draws his conclusions from the same.</p>
               <p>Pag. 21. <hi>He saith, speaking of the said Declaration, that it doth not follow, that the offence was judged by a Law afterwards made, for that the Law was made before, upon the change of Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Under favor of this nameless Author; if any man, who before this Declaration was made, had adhered unto the Son of the late King, He may by this Declaration afterwards made, be proceeded against as a Traytor, and his Estate be Confiscated: For the words are, (<hi>have</hi> Adhered) as well as those that <hi>shall</hi> adhere: And what greater argument can there be, that that Declaration was never intended as a Law, to reach the Lives and Estates of the People of <hi>England,</hi> for doing of things before that Declaration was made: We have a promise declared by Act of Parliament, that Laws of that Nature shall not be drawn into Example.</p>
               <p>Pag. 8. <hi>He undertakes to tell you what the Crime was which the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>committed against the Declaration of the</hi> 24. <hi>of</hi> Aug. 1649. <hi>for saith he, the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>converse and familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the King of</hi> Scots <hi>at</hi> Breda, <hi>and in the Privy-chambers with the King; and otherwise (being saith he, adherency to the Enemy of this Commonwealth) is consequently Treason by the known Laws of the Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> This man undertakes to name the Child, which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to was never done by the Parliament who adjudged the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> an Offender; for they never declared to this day what his Offence was.</p>
               <p>They only declared the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was an Offender within such a Declaration, but never expressed for what; whether for <hi>Aid, Assistance</hi> or <hi>Adherencie</hi> to the King of <hi>Scots;</hi> nor was his Crime ever yet named, or reduced into any charge, that he might know it, and thereby make a legal defence.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119472:6"/>
               <p>What is an Adherency, is described by that famous Lawyer, the Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> in his Pleas of the Crown, which is a giving of Ayd, Comfort or Assistance, which by the Declaration is not only to be given to the Son of the late King, but <hi>against</hi> the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> otherwise it is not within that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and if that be so, notwithstanding the confidence of that nameless Author, the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Crime is yet as much to seek as ever it was, which was never yet declared or known; though his Estate be confiscate, sold and gone.</p>
               <p>Pag. 2. <hi>He saith, That the Commissioners for Comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sitions being unresolved, whether the Declaration of the</hi> 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>of</hi> Aug. 1649. <hi>did intend that the Estates of such Persons shall be sequestred, who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, and there have held Correspondency with the King of</hi> Scots, <hi>during their abode beyond the Seas; and therefore desired <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n explanation therein by the Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per presented by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, recited at large in the Narrative.</note> Here this nameless Author again deals deceitfully with the Reader, and most impudently and falsely fixes the scruple of the Commissioners for Compositions, as grounded upon the Declaration of the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1649▪ &amp; so would fortifie the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve of Parliament as grounded upon a scruple of that Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whereas they in their Paper delivered to the Council of State &amp; read in Parliament, did not so much as mention the said Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, nor any clause thereof; Nor was matter of Confiscation properly in Judgement before them; nor did they proceed upon that Declaration against any man, till by an additional Vote upon occasion of debate of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Case, they were enabled thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Vote of <hi>Confiscation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Pag. 3. <hi>The unknowing Author saith, That the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>upon the Order of Confiscation of his Estate, addressed not, or applyed himself unto the Parliament in any Petition; thereby endeavouring to acquit himself before those his proper Judges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> This is an untruth, fit only to be owned by the father of untruths; for the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> besides the several Petitions delivered by others who were ready to undertake on his behalf, and that Petition delivered in <hi>August</hi> 1651. subscribed by his Lordship in his own hand, which was presented to the Parliament, and not finding a reception thereof, did address himself to the Parliament by another Petition (which last Petition, and a Dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thereof had been in several Members hands nine moneths before) in expectation of an opportunity to present the same to the House; and at last came to be read in Parliament the 22 of <hi>June</hi> 1652. In which Petition he doth particularly take notice of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119472:7"/> the Votes of the 6 of <hi>March</hi> 1650. and therein asserts the falshood of <hi>Faulconers</hi> Information, and his own innocence to the matter informed against him; and humbly prayes that the Parliament (even that Parliament that condemned him unheard) would put his business into such away, as that he might be heard in his just defence by his Counsell: But the Parliament, as by their Votes of that day, entered and remaining in the Journal Book appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, thought not fit to give way unto it, but on the contrary past a Vote (at that very time when his Lordship desired to acquit himself) to condemn his Estate to sale, without further hearing of him; and yet the unknowing Author would have the world to know that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> did decline the Judicature of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament in the determination of his Cause, which no man that is not blinde with Malice could suggest.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for the forementioned Votes of Confiscation of the sixth of <hi>March</hi> 1650. it is observable, that they are without any charge or accusation in themselves, nor do they refer to any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, or other complaint or charge whatsoever depending in Parliament against him, to which he was called, or might an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, had his Lordship been here; which as it is not Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the proceedings, so it remains still at the door of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, crying for a due examination, and that so great a Reproach may be taken from the Nation, who cannot but suffer under such unparalleld proceeding; for albeit the Parliament will not suffer their Power to be limited by others, yet certainly there are Rules as well and certainly known, as to the proceedings in Parliament against any mans Person and Estate, as any Rule at the Common-law; &amp; when in time to come it shall be said that no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident can be shewed of a man condemned, either by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or Judgement in Parliament, against whom there was not some Charge, Accusation, or Impeachment depending in Parliament, or some Indictment or Proceedings in some other Court, sent for and removed into Parliament, and whereunto the Party might make his answer, but that of the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> men will certainly think him a prodigy that brought the Crime of his Confiscation into the World with him.</p>
               <p>The great Charter of the Peoples Liberties, for which so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Battails were fought, and so much blood and treasure spent for so many Ages together, was made sacred by the solemn Oaths of our Fore-fathers for them and theirs, and also by a Law in the 42<seg rend="sup">th</seg> year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, whereby it is Enacted, if any Parliament do ordain any thing contrary to the Concessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it shall be void; and as a testimony thereof, the said Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute as the true touchstone of all <hi>English</hi> Interests, hath been confirmed in Parliament above thirty times; and by the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by divers Acts, and especially by an Act of the 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119472:7"/>
                  <hi>February</hi> 1648. Who once declared, that they would maintain that Law which says, No man should be outed of his freehold, but by lawful Judgement of his Peers or by the Law of the Land; and to say truth, there was Reason for them so to do, considering that the Statute of the 25<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. Enacts that none be put out of his freehold, unless he be duly brought in to answer by due process of Law.</p>
               <p>The Statute of the 28<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                  <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. to avoid the mischief done to the People by false accusers, doth Enact that no man be put to answer without due presentment before Justices or matter of Record, or by due process according to the Law of the Land; and if any thing be henceforth done to the contrary, it shall be void in Law and holden for Errour; now to those forementioned Laws, not only Judgements and proceedings in Parliament as well as in all other Courts of Record ought to be conformable; for as former Parliaments have Enacted that no persons be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, unless by due process of Law he be first brought to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; so it hath been constantly held and practised for Law, that if the Parliament had at any time proceeded upon an insufficient Charge, and that the condemnation of the party had thereupon followed; (he not taking advantage thereof) the heirs of the parties that have fallen under such Judgements have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to reverse such Judgements against their Ancestors, by saying that there was no Charge or legal Accusation to which they might answer; The several Judgements given in Parliament against <hi>Edward Mortimer</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi> against <hi>John Matravers,</hi> were reversed as being contrary to the Law to try a man without a Crime, or to put him to answer without a Charge; as appears by the Parliament Rolls, 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and 29. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords do express that to be the reason and none other; And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Law was so taken to be in the late Parliament, when that memorable Person Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> once a Member of the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, who in his Speech in the Earl of <hi>Straffords</hi> Case concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Breaches made upon the Law, (applicable to powers as well as to Persons) saith, <hi>That the Law is the safeguard, the custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of all private Interest;</hi> our honours, our Lives, our Liberties and Estates are all in keeping of the Law; without this every man hath a like right to any thing; all things will fall into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion; every man will become a Law to himself, which in the depraved condition of humane nature must needs produce many great enormities; Lust will become a Law, and Envy will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Law, Covetousness and Ambition will become Laws.</p>
               <p>Pag. 5. <hi>The unknown Author saith, that the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>friends supposed he received hard measure in being judged before he was heard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> It is sad that any man should account a condemnation of a person (unheard) but a supposed hard measure, which (indeed)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119472:8"/> was hard measure in the highest degree: When <hi>Adam</hi> did trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress, God very well knew what he had done, yet God would not condemn him till he had asked him where he was, what he had done, and had first heard what he could say for himself: The like saith God unto the Woman; and after both their answers, then God pronounces sentence upon them: The like dealing did God use towards <hi>Cain,</hi> for though he knew that he had murthered his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> yet God requires an account of him, and had his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to it before he pronounces Judgement upon him.</p>
               <p>Pag. 23. <hi>He saith the Parliament upon the proof aforesaid, and for</hi> reasons best known <hi>to themselves in time of general</hi> Imbroylments; <hi>Ordered the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Estate to be</hi> confiscated; <hi>yet they ordered it not to be</hi> sold, <hi>but the Rents thereof were</hi> gathered, <hi>which are done ordinarily in order to Tryal and Judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> Now he begins a little to weaken the validity of his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses testimony, and to help it out with this, That the Parliament for <hi>Reasons best known</hi> to themselves had confiscated the L. <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate: The Reasons of Parliaments to take away any mans Life and Estate, ought to be known to others as well as to themselves; and if the results of their reasons appear not upon Record by way of Charge, Impeachment, or Indictment, and that the party by due course of Law be called to answer unto the same: It is not for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons best known to themselves will justifie a Judgement that will reach a mans livelihood and estate, which by all Laws in the world is left to the Owner so long as he is thought fit to live; but in some particular cases of a near nature, Parliaments after a Judgement of life or estate, have added, a saving that it be not drawn into example to preserve the like Cases for their own Judgements; but for the unknown Author to say, for reasons best known to themselves they did confiscate his Estate, is in his sense, to say no more, then that they did it because they had a mind to it: He would also help out that <hi>hasty</hi> Vote of Confiscation yet further, in that it was passed in time of general <hi>Imbroylments;</hi> which is most false; for there was not in all <hi>England,</hi> either field-force, or garrison of the enemies at that time: And if there had been <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broylments,</hi> was that any just warrant to condemn any man beyond the Seas (unheard) and concerning whom there was never any question before them.</p>
               <p>Then he saith further in excuse, That though his Estate was confiscated, yet it was not sold; for the Rents were gathered, as in case of Sequestration; here is still a mistake which the nameless Author is subject unto; for as soon as ever the Vote of Confiscation passed, his personal Estate throughout all <hi>England</hi> (which was of no small value) was seized upon as confiscate and sold, and much of it bought by Members of that Parliament who condemned him unheard, and who probably had then in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119472:8"/> their eye the purchase of his Estate; for some of them ever after that Vote of Confiscation, violently pressed on the sale of his Estate, and bought large possessions thereof at easy peny worths; It was not the Bill of Sale which passed <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. 1652. which confiscated the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate, but the Vote of Confisca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>March</hi> 1650. for the Bill of Sale did onely order the sale of the Estate forfeited, but did not create the Forfeiture; &amp; if that were admitted to the Author, that the Vote went but to the profits and not to the Confiscation of the Estate; It is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally thought that the Author may easier find out <hi>Faulconers</hi> honesty, then a real difference between the thing it self and profits of it, and the Philosophers stone then either: And for the Nameless Author to compare this Confiscation to the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon a Sequestration, is the greatest errour that can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; For this is the known and just Rule which is punctually observed by those prudent Gentlemen, the Commissioners for Compositions sitting at <hi>Habberdashers-hall,</hi> not so much as to seize upon and secure any mans Estate, Rents or goods in the Tenants hands, till they have received probable testimony to prove the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency; and when they have so secured the Estate, they receive not a peny thereof, but reduce their proof into a Charge, give the Delinquent a copy thereof appoint him a time to make his defence, give him leave to examine witnesses, nay to cross-examine the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses that are sworn against him, and to except against them for perjury if there be cause, &amp; then give him leave to be heard by his councel (&amp; not condemn him unheard) &amp; after the hearing, in case they be not satisfied upon the defence, that they ought to clear the Delinquent, to pronounce Sequestration of his Estate, not upon a single witnes, but upon the testimony of two at the least; and then and not before they issue out an Order to receive the Rents and profits of the Delinquents Lands: This just kind of dealing might the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> have had before these Commissioners, even in case of Sequestration, had he been so happy as to come before them: But whether he received the like in case of Confiscation, is left to the Reader to think, and the World to judge.</p>
               <p>Pag. 1. <hi>He saith, It is most false, that upon the single testimony of</hi> Faulconer, <hi>that scandalous and perjured Person, the Parliament had Enacted the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Estate to be sold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> It will be made good too, or upon the whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling Author whensoever he will pull off his vizard, and shew himself bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, That by and upon the single testimony of that since per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured person <hi>Faulconer</hi> (as to matter of crime carrying with it Treason and Confiscation) the late Parliament did by Vote Confiscate the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate (unheard) and afterwards Enacted the same to be sold, refusing to hear proof against that perjured witness before the Bill of Sale did pass,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119472:9"/> for what the other two witnesses <hi>Reyly</hi> and <hi>Kitchingman</hi> do say, That the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was with the King at <hi>Breda,</hi> in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, at <hi>the Table,</hi> and Bowling-Alley, carries not Treason or cause of Confiscation along with it, for there is not the least proof by either of those witnesses, that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> spoke one word against the Parliament at his being at <hi>Breda,</hi> whilest the King was there; nor do they, or either of them say any one word that may point that way. Besides, he did not repair out of these Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the King, but the King repaired out of these Dominions into <hi>Holland,</hi> where the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> residence was, and so had been for above twenty years before, and was then attending his Charge there under the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in the service of the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> as he was bound by the Oath of his Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by whose Command, and in whose Attendance he came to <hi>Breda.</hi> The word of God saith, <hi>That in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word shall be established.</hi> And by the Statute of 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. there must be two witnesses to convict any one of Treason: Whether these Rules have been observed in the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Case, the Reader is left to judge: But what was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in proof against the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to make him a Delinquent, he had a good and free Estate (a snare and Temptation to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) and his offence was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oner believed then known by his Judges, who were purchasers of his Estate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Summons.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Nameless Author saith</hi> Pag. 5. <hi>That upon the sollicitation of some Friends of the Lord</hi> Cravens, <hi>the Parliament the third of</hi> July <hi>following, Ordered a Summons to be issued out, proclaimed and printed, requiring and commanding the said</hi> William <hi>Lord</hi> Craven <hi>by the Authority of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>to make his personal appearance before the Parliament the third of</hi> September 1651. <hi>there to make answer to all such matters as should be objected against him in the behalf of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, <hi>whereof he is not to fail at his Peril, which was printed and proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accordingly. And</hi> Pag. 25. <hi>saith, the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>not accepting the favour of a Summons, his Name was put into the Bill of Sale for his Lands to be sold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I enter upon any Answer hereunto, I would ask the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing Author whether he thinks he said any thing for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters honour, or can he say any thing less then this; that they first confiscated the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate, and then summoned his Person to hear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he could say for himself; <hi>Certainly the Bishop hath forgotten that ever he was a Clerk:</hi> his Masters could not be so ignorant of the proceedings of all the known Judicatories un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun, which judge no man in Person or Estate, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119472:9"/> upon an Answer, or for the contempt of the Party, as refusing the Law; but since he will have it granted to him that they did so, I will tell the Author of his unheard of Justification, what I conceive of it and him.</p>
               <p>First, It is most scandalously untrue, that any of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Friends did sollicite or endeavour that he might be then summoned; for the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Friends very well knew that there was no Cause for any such desire on his Lordships be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, there being no Charge or Impeachment depending in Parliament, to which judicially and legally he could then be sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to come and answer; and this will undeniably be evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to any man of understanding, by the Petition preferred by his Lordships Friends on his Lordships behalf and read in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that very day the Order for Summons was conceived and brought forth, thereby setting forth, that his Lordship being far beyond the Seas in the parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> at the time of the passing of the votes of Confiscation, knew nothing of the Votes against him here in <hi>England;</hi> and therefore did humbly pray on the behalf of the said Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> that they might be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to send an express unto his Lordship to acquaint him with the said Votes; but the Parliament (that or what else could be said for his Lordship, notwithstanding did summon the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> to appear within two Moneths, he being then in <hi>Germany</hi> 800 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles distant from <hi>London</hi>) were not pleased to permit the Petitioners to send to the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to give him notice of the proceedings in Parliament against him, nor to order the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to be personally served upon him according to Law (he having passed out of <hi>England</hi> by licence of Parliament into <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a place then in amity with this Nation) onely ordered the same to be printed, and published at the Old Exchange <hi>London,</hi> and in <hi>Westminster-hall,</hi> that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> might at his peril take notice thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is to be observed, that the Vote of Confiscation of the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>March</hi> 1650. and the seizure thereupon of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate, was before the Order for summoning of the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> about five moneths; And none of the free People of <hi>England,</hi> who are out of <hi>England,</hi> ought to incur any forfeiture for their contempt, in not returning into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> without a personal Summons under some of the seals of the Commonwealth, which the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> hath not yet had, nor was any left for him in <hi>Holland</hi> where his Command was.</p>
               <p>And therefore to inform the judgement of the unknown Author, against the time that I shall have the occasion of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, or he himself better; I will shortly shew him, how the Law of this Nation that set the Meer-stones to, &amp; raised the Hay &amp; Hedge about every mans Estate, was before that Vote of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscation,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119472:10"/> and the Summons sent to the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> at the time of the proceeding against him, and is at this day: It cannot be denied but that by the Course of the Common Law, every man might pass the Seas for merchandize or travail without licence, unless he were by the Writ, <hi>de securitate invenienda quod se non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertat ad partes exteras sine licentia Regis,</hi> commanded to the contrary, and so the Law continued untill the Statute of 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. did forbid and defend the passages utterly of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of People (except the Lords and great Ones of the Realm, and true and notable Merchants, and the Kings Soldiers) to pass out of the Realm without the Kings especial licence, under the pain of forfeiting of all his goods; and that Act continued until the Statute of 4 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1. which repeals the Act of King <hi>Rich.</hi> the second, and sets the Ports open again, and so they remain at this day; that is to say, any man may pass beyond the Seas without licence (if there be no inhibition to the contrary) into any Countrey in amity with our Nation; but to make the Case short and full, the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> passed the Seas by licence of the same Parliament that confiscated his Estate and exposed it to Sale, for that he was beyond the Seas; that is to say, for not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing upon a Summons made at <hi>Westminster,</hi> when his Lordship was in <hi>Germany,</hi> warranted in his being there, by his Letters of licence; then the Question is, whether his Lordship ought not to have been prrsonally summoned, especially having passed himself beyond the Seas by licence; It is common in the Exchequer to find seizures, <hi>Quia recusavit declinare se in regnum per mandatum Domini Regis,</hi> and so was the Case of <hi>William de Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> E. of <hi>Richmond,</hi> whose goods were seized, because he disobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Summons of return served personally upon him in <hi>Gascoign,</hi> this Record you may find in 19. <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>in Sca.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>M. Dy.</hi> 128. <hi>p.</hi> 61. It is agreed by all the Judges, that albeit the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had gone beyond the Seas without licence, yet to induce a forfeiture, he must be in contempt, which could not be without a special Commandment under the great Seal or privy Seal sent to him there to return, 2 <hi>Eliz. Dy.</hi> 176. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>Bartu</hi> and the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chess of <hi>Suffolk</hi> passed the Seas by licence: <hi>Bret</hi> the Officer that went with the privy Seal to recall them, was forced to swear the service upon them, which he did, specially not being permitted to come to them by the servants of <hi>Bartu</hi> and the Dutchess, but that in their presence he did it, and there it is admitted without scruple, that the Summons ought to be to his Person, and so is the opinion of the Judges of both the Benches, and the chief Baron, 13. <hi>El. Dy.</hi> 296. <hi>p.</hi> 19. and that the Parliament was of that Judgment, it will clearly appear by a Statute made that same year, 13. <hi>El. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Rastal,</hi> whereby it is Enacted that they that have gone beyond the Seas without licence, and do not return within six
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119472:10"/> Moneths after Proclamation made under the great Seal of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> shall forfeit the profits of their Estates; but he that passed the Sea by licence, had by that Statute six Moneths after the expiration of his licence to make his return: for the Law was then taken, that such a licence being for a time, it was not revokable by the King himself: Vpon this Act was the Estate of Sir <hi>Francis Englefield</hi> forfeited; but he had first refused to come home; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing personally served with a privy Seal he was out-lawed for Treason in 26 <hi>El.</hi> in the Kings Bench, and that attainder confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Act of Parliament in the 28<seg rend="sup">th</seg> year of her Raign: &amp; if you look into the Pattent Rolls, you will find <hi>Pat.</hi> 1 <hi>El. ps.</hi> 4. a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to Sir <hi>Francis Englefield</hi> to pass the Sea to the <hi>Baynes</hi> for his health, and all this before that any part of his Estate was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscated in Vote or otherwise; and why my Lord <hi>Craven</hi> should not have the same fair play for his Estate that Sir <hi>Francis Engle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> had, who stood out-lawed of Treason before any thing was done more then the seizure of the profits for refusing to return, puts me into great wonder; It cannot be the difference of Estates, that could cause this diversity of Proceedings; for of cerain Sir <hi>Francis Englefield</hi> had an Estate not much inferiour to my Lord; and since the difference was not in the quarry, it cannot be else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where then in the keeness of the Guests.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, If a Charge be in Parliament against any one being in <hi>England</hi> at that time, and afterwards goes beyond the Seas, Proclamation may be in <hi>England</hi> to summon him by a day, for that the Charge attached upon him being here, where he might have known what is done; and if he comes not, Judgement may be given against him upon his Flight, as it was in Sir <hi>Giles Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestons</hi> Case, in the Parliament of 18 <hi>Jac.</hi> and as it was in the Case of <hi>Thomas Mortimer</hi> 21 <hi>R.</hi> 2. and in the Case of the Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> 7 <hi>H.</hi> 4. and in the case of divers persons, who being in <hi>England</hi> at the time when they were impeached in the <hi>late Parliament</hi> of high Treason and other misdeameanors, fled, and were thereupon proceeded against by Proclamation in the nature of a Summons, which did issue forth under the great Seal, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them to answer the <hi>Impeachments</hi> depending in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but without a Charge or Impeachment, there can be no Proceedings or Forfeiture by any Rule of Law or known Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Parliament, unless the party being in <hi>England</hi> at the time of the Charge upon Proclamation made for his appearance, do not appear at the time; but if he be beyond the Seas at the time of the offence, as also of the Charge drawn upon him; no For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture or Contempt can be fastened upon him without a personal Summons under Seal.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, This being the Law of <hi>England,</hi> that without a Charge depending in Parliament against one beyond the Seas for a Crime committed there, and a personal Summons thereupon,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119472:11"/> the life and Estate of such persons ought not to be taken away and forfeited; and the late Parliament having by their Declaration of the 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Februry</hi> 1648. declared as followeth, <hi>That they are fully resolved to maintain, and shall and will uphold, preserve and keep the fundamental Laws of this Nation, for, and concerning the preservation of the lives, properties and liberties of the people with all things inciden thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would therefore be very much for the honour of this present Parliament to give relief to the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> who so contrary to Law and the fundamental Rules in Parliament hath had his Estate confiscate and sold, and himself forejudged his native Countrey as an Exile.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The words of the Summons are further observable: <hi>viz.</hi> To answer such things as <hi>shall be objected</hi> against him, a thing frequently used by the Lords of the Councel when Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative was uppermost, and by other Arbitrary Powers in those times; but till now it was never known in Parliament, neither was it ever alledged or thought a Contempt for not appearing to what should be objected against a man, or made a ground by Parliament to forfeit Life and Estate; The Old Law of <hi>England</hi> being that if a man, who had a personal Summons under Seal le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally served upon him, and did not accordingly appear, his Estate for the Contempt was only to be seized <hi>quousque</hi> until he should come, and there was not to be any Forfeiture and Sale of his Estate; but if the Summons had been to answer unto such things as <hi>shall</hi> be objected against him, and for which his Estate <hi>is already confiscated</hi> and shall satisfie, then there had been something towards his Information as to the Crime: and albeit he knew not the Offence, yet he knew the price of it, be it what it will.</p>
               <p>He saith, Pag. 24. <hi>That the Lord Cravens not appearing upon the Summons, must needs argue his Guilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> This is but a meer surmise of the Nameless Author: for there were other Reasons which might more justly make the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> scruple his coming over at that time.</p>
               <p>First, He was declared an Offendor within a dubious Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>unheard</hi> by the Lawmakers themselves, which tyed up the Judgement of Inferiour Courts and Judges, before whom he might have been tried if he were such an Offendor, (as by the Vote he was declared to be) and his Life would then have been in equal danger with his Estate; To say the truth, it had argued his Lordship guilty of little care of his Person, if he had put himself into the hands of his Prosecutor who had already got his Estate confiscate <hi>quibusdam certis de Causis,</hi> an expression cast out of an evil spirit hating Law, Rule and Order.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That his Estate was thereupon confiscated unheard,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119472:11"/> and all his personal Estate seized upon and sold before Summons, which issued not until some Moneths after that Confiscation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That some of his Judges when his Estate was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscated <hi>(unheard)</hi> bought much of his goods, and were thereby <hi>engaged;</hi> and who afterwards violently pressed on the Sale of his Land, which some of them afterwards bought to make them Competent Judges of his life, might require a Consideration.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The Summons was not according to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> nor the Course of Proceedings in Parliament, nor of any known Law since it was said, I will hear him when his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuser comes.</p>
               <p>Before the Summons issued forth, the Parliament upon solemn debate refused to resume the consideration of that <hi>eager</hi> Vote of <hi>Confiscation,</hi> in order to a revoking or suspention thereof; what then might his Lordship expect, when such a Resolution had passed in confirmation of the Confiscation of his Estate, or to what end should he appear in <hi>England,</hi> when he had nothing left him but his Liberty and his Credit to live of?</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The Parliament after several applications made unto them, desiring <hi>Faulconers</hi> Perjury might be examined, thought not fit to give way unto it.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, And before the Bill of Sale did pass, the Parliament was informed by Petition on behalf of his Lordship, that an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment of Perjury was found against <hi>Faulconer;</hi> but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they thought not fit to permit the business to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Parliament, but proceeded to the Sale, and themselves stept in first to buy.</p>
               <p>Pag. 23. <hi>He saith, The Parliament cannot be supposed to be so unworthy and treacherous, as to order a man to appear to answer to Crimes laid to his Charge, and then to take away his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> The Summons of the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was to appear to answer to the Crime objected against him, then and yet unknown to him or any other but his Prosecutor, who wanted neither malice, nor bitterness of spirit to promote their design against him; the Examinations of <hi>Faulconer</hi> who is <hi>single</hi> and indeed hath no fellow for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deadly sins, can be no legal Charge to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer unto; for they are but things preparatory out of which a Legal Charge, Indictment or Impeachment may be framed, if there be matter for it; and it was the constant practice in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to put to the Question every Article in a Charge or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment against any Person; <hi>viz.</hi> whether upon the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which the Chairman reported, they conceive the Article so fully proved, as to pass the same for an Article in the Charge or Impeachment; such was the care of the late Parliament of the Lives and Estates of the People at their first sitting (though it was not practised in the Conclusion) and afterwards the Parties
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119472:12"/> impeached were heard upon the Charge, and not condemned without a <hi>Charge</hi> or <hi>unheard;</hi> And when Parliaments leave their known Rules, be their intentions never so upright, those that are by them declared and adjudged Offenders contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the known Law, may justly fear their lives to be in danger as well as their Estate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He saith,</hi> Pag. 2. <hi>That the Council of State received Information against the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>of five several men, and made oath of before the Commissioners,</hi> Anno 1650. <hi>and</hi> Pa. 3. <hi>That upon reading the said Depositions, the Votes of Confiscation passed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> This is most false: for only <hi>Faulconers, Reylyes</hi> and <hi>Kitchingmans</hi> Examinations were presented to, and read in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, when the Votes of Confiscation did pass; and had there been any more Examinations, that would have made the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> look like a Delinquent, there wanted not good will in the Prosecutor, to improve the same to the uttermost advantage of himself, as well as of the Commonwealth; Nor afterwards from the time of Confiscation, which was in <hi>March</hi> 1650. till <hi>August</hi> 1652. that the Bill of Sale did pass, was there any other Examination read in Parliament ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inst the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> or any Charge or Impeachment grounded upon any Examinations what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever in all that time.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But then he tells you,</hi> Pag. 49. <hi>That there are proofs of another Nature sufficient to confiscate the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Estate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> If that <hi>hastier</hi> Vote of Confiscation may be Repealed, and the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> restored to his Estate again, the Nameless Author may then proceed with a Charge containing new matter, and the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> will, and then may (upon equal Terms) appear in person, and abide his Trial; otherwise it will be too like <hi>Halifax</hi> Law to condemn a man, and then inquire out a Cause for it afterwards; for so it is to confiscate and expose to Sale an Estate, and then afterwards to offer out new matter to warrant the same, which was not under judgement either at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscation or Sale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119472:12"/>
               <head>The Address in <hi>Holland,</hi> called an APPEAL.</head>
               <p>HItherto the Author hath defended the Confiscation for Reasons best known to the late Parliament, now he shifts his sail, and seems to defend it for Reasons best known to the States of <hi>Holland; For he tells us,</hi> Pag. 3. <hi>The Lord</hi> Craven <hi>waving the Power and Jurisdiction of the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>though the said Lord was a native Member and Subject of</hi> England; <hi>and the matter charged against him, being Treason against the said Commonwealth,</hi> De Groot <hi>Agent for the Prince Elector</hi> Palatine, <hi>the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>very good and obliged Friend, at the</hi> Hague <hi>appealed in the said Lords Case, and on his behalf, from the judgement of the Parliament of this Commonwealth, to the States General of the united Provinces of the</hi> Netherlands, <hi>being a forreign State,</hi> May 13. 1651.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Here the nameless Author endeavours to draw a belief in the Reader, that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> had waved the Jurisdiction of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and had appealed to the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the united Provinces, then which nothing is more false, and the Conscience of this unknowing Author must needs fly in his face; for that the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> was 400 miles from the <hi>Hague</hi> at that time, and that what address was made to those States, was by the Orders of the Prince Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> and by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to his Agent with that State, and only to obtain a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommendation of the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Case to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> whose Embassadors were then there negotiating a firm Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But because that unknown Author further taketh upon him</hi> (Pag. 3.) <hi>to relate the particulars of that which was called an appeal in</hi> Holland, <hi>although he hath interlarded it with his own observations almost in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry line, and hath omitted very much contained in that Paper called an Appeal; that every one that reads it, may see the malice and mistakes of that nameless Author.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You shall have the words thereof <hi>verbatim,</hi> as also the Prince Electors Letter, the grounds of that Address, as the same are now remaining upon Record in Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119472:13"/>
               <head>The Prince Electors Letter.</head>
               <p>OUr friendly service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Forasmuch as we have given our faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Resident, <hi>Peter de Groot,</hi> a Commission to propound unto your Lordships <hi>on our be, half</hi> in a matter <hi>about the Lord</hi> Craven; therefore it is our friendly request to your Lordships, to grant him a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Audience, and to give full credit to his Message, and to be mindful of the said Lord <hi>Craven</hi> in his affairs; in regard that he hath been many years in your service, and hath done much good service to us and our Electoral Family, and to hold him specially recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and we shall acknowledge such favour as though it were done to our selves, and upon all occasions seek to requite herewith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Exhibitum <date>
                        <hi>the 31 of May 1651.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>High and Mighty Lords,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IN pursuance of the verbal Proposition made this day in your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Assembly by his Electoral Highness, my Lord and Master, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to his Missive Letter of the <hi>10/20</hi> of this Moneth, in the business of my Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> I have put in writing, and thereunto annexed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions made or contrived against the said Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which followed thereon, the Confiscation of his Goods which rose upon it, the execution thereof decreed and partly done, with a confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the said Depositions, and a demonstration of the Nullities, as well as of the Injustice committed in the said Condemnation: That your Honours according to your accustomed goodness in relieving and assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the oppressed, besides the merits of the Person, and the earnest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of his Electoral Highness, especially considering the justness of the matter for redress of your credit, and the opportunity which is given you by occasion of the <hi>Alliance with England now in hand,</hi> will be pleased to take such a course, as that the Deponents may be punished as perjured Calumniators, the Condemnation wrongfully done be annulled, and my Lord <hi>Craven</hi> be put again into the former possession and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of his rightful goods: The <hi>Depositions</hi> are three in number, whereof the first is ridiculous, the other two utterly false: If they were sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be all true, I have in the Margent confuted them to be frivolous, and confirmed the confutation with true Certificates or Attestations, so as the Condemnation upon them cannot but be unjust: it is further void, because it is not applicable to the matter, considering the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whence it is formed (it only concerning those, who falling to the Kings side from the Parliaments service, are declared for Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Rebells) considering the Person (who besides he never served
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119472:13"/> the Parliament, and so cannot have been either Rebell or Traitor: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that he never gave any such assistance or aid to the King, yea is <hi>not charged</hi> therewith in his Accusations, how false soever they be: also du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all that time was out of the Countrey, whom according to the Laws of <hi>England</hi> it self, (a new Law made in his absence cannot prejudice except it appear that he had notice of it) And considering your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, who without a weakning of your Power and Honour, cannot suffer that a Person, who is not only an <hi>Inhabitant,</hi> but a sworn <hi>Servant</hi> of this State, should be condemned in a Countrey who are in <hi>mutual Amity</hi> and <hi>correspondence</hi> with your Lordships for Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Duty towards this State; and by <hi>Order of his Highness,</hi> as Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, done and performed amongst your Honours, <hi>his</hi> Lords and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters; All which being considered, your Honours are intreated, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the matter which is so just and important, amounting to about <hi>150000</hi> Gilders <hi>per annum;</hi> in respect of the person, who besides the twenty years service that he hath done this State, hath so bountifully distributed his means in this Countrey in respect of your Honours own Authority, who according to the <hi>Declaration</hi> there anent, made about the <hi>Persons of the English Merchants</hi> at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> do not permit that any of their Inhabitants (I forbear to say sworn ones) be bound to another State without their knowledge and consent; And in respect of the special <hi>recommendation of his Electoral Highness,</hi> your Honours would please to be so mindful of the said Lord <hi>Craven</hi> and his business, that he may be put again into the full possession of his Goods, so as he hath been formerly seized of them by revocation, annullation, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise of cancelling or avoiding the aforesaid condemnation, and the effect thereof: That your Honours would be pleased to grant your <hi>special Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Recommendation</hi> for that purpose to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest the Embassadors</hi> here for the <hi>like Recommendation</hi> &amp; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours: and if need require, to make the same in your <hi>Treaties</hi> with the Embassadors of <hi>England,</hi> as hath been deemed to be done in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the like nature: Assuring your Honours, that the said Lord <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> shall be alwayes ready to employ his said Estate to the benefit or good of this Countrey and her Inhabitants: and that his Electoral Highness, besides the many other engagements which he is obliged to this State, shall also account this as particularly done to his person or family, and shall take hold of all opportunities for to shew his thankfulness therefore to this State and Inhabitants.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119472:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> English <hi>Embassadors then in</hi> Holland <hi>having notice of this adderss, certified the Parliament thereof; yet the Parliament did not so much as reduce that into any Charge against the Lord</hi> Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>neither was there any Cause it should be objected as a Charge against him, it not appearing he was privy to it, besides he was 400. miles distant from the</hi> Hague <hi>at that time: and it plainly appearing by the thing it self that it was not made by him, but by</hi> De Groot, <hi>by the express direction of the Prince Elector, whose Agent</hi> De Groot <hi>was, and then Resident for his Highness with the States of</hi> Holland: <hi>&amp; therefore that cannot or ought not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as any good Ground to take away the Life and Estate of the Lord</hi> Craven: <hi>I have now shewed you the Credentials of</hi> Mounsieur De Groot, <hi>and his paper which by his Lords and Masters Order, he put in before the States of</hi> Holland <hi>in consequence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which bespeaks only their mediation in his Lordships behalf, as a person that by long service to them, and a constant Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Electoral Family, had merited from them, and from his Highness the Prince Elector, such succors, as by themselves or their Alliances they might best afford him in so great a storm and distress of his Estate and fortune.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning that Infamous Person <hi>Faulconer,</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convicted of a foul and palpable Perjury.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe unknowing Author saith,</hi> Pag. 14. 15. <hi>That several single witnesses were produced to blemish the Conversation of</hi> Faulconer: <hi>and</hi> Pag. 48. <hi>saith, That the Narrator doth with Deceit, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and untruth, designedly blemish the Justice of the proceedings of Parliament, and to undermine the Act by which the Lord</hi> Cravens <hi>Estate is by them adjudged to be sold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> A man cannot speak Truth, that <hi>Faulconer</hi> is a perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Person, or that he was in <hi>Newgate</hi> and other Gaols for suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Felony, Robbery and Murder, and endeavored to bugger a man, or that he drunk an Health to the Devil, swore wounds &amp; blood he would bugger a mans soul to Hell, or that he said that our Saviour Jesus Christ was a Bastard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But it must tend to blemish and undermine the Judgement and Proceedings of the late Parliament, and cast aspersions on the Conversation of <hi>Faulconer</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed, when the Narrator offers any thing that carries Justice, Reason and Truth with it, and crosses the design of the unknown Author against the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> then he flies to this Argument, The Parliament is undermined: the Judgement of Parliament is questioned.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119472:14"/>
               <p>If the late Parliament had been pleased, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of several petitions to them presented, to have given way that the Informations as to <hi>Faulconers</hi> perjury in the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Case, (he being a single witness) and his abominable course of Life might have been examined in Parliament, themselves might have been the Judges thereof, which by their refusal came to be heard in the Court of Upper-Bench, where it held six hours Trial: and the said <hi>Faulconer</hi> was there by the Oaths of twelve good and true Men (nominated by the Court) convicted of false Perjury.</p>
               <p>And seeing the unknowing Author speaks so much of the Judgement of Parliament against the said Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> he must know, that what passed in Parliament against the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver passed with the clear Judgement of Parliament, but it met with great and high opposition, though by majority of voices it was concluded against him; for the Parliament was four times divided about the Lord <hi>Craven;</hi> the first time of division it was carried but by one single voice, the second time by two, the third time by three, and the fourth time by four voices: and when it was put to the question, whether the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> name should stand in the ingrossed Act for Sale, there were upon the divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the House, twenty in the negative, and only twenty three Members in the affirmative, and nine Members have contracted for near 5000 l. <hi>per annum:</hi> of the Lo. <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate, as appears by the Books at <hi>Drury-house;</hi> besides what is bought in other mens names for the use of Members of that Parliament; and those Members who were then in the late Parliament, and bore their witness against that <hi>more</hi> then <hi>hasty</hi> Vote of Confiscation, and the proceedings thereupon against the Lord <hi>Craven unheard,</hi> or without a <hi>Charge,</hi> were Persons of Honour, Wisdom, Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Judgement; and if called (no doubt) will express the grounds of their great disassent to, and dissatisfaction of the proceedings against his Lordship (as being without instance in time) and the violence of the prosecution.</p>
               <p>And whereas he saith, there were several single witnesses pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced against <hi>Faulconer</hi> at his Tryal; I appeal to that great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory who were then present, (being as many as that large Court of Upper-Bench was able to receive) to witness; whether as to the proof of this main Charge of <hi>Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> against him, it was only proved by a single witness; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r whereas <hi>Faulconer</hi> swore that in this Petition (pretended to be) promoted by the Lord <hi>Craven</hi> at <hi>Breda,</hi> the Petitioners did desire <hi>to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained to serve the King of</hi> Scots <hi>against the Parliament of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>by the name of Barbarous and Inhumane Rebells;</hi> It was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by three witnesses produced in Court, who read the Petition
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119472:15"/> and signed it, (one of them being <hi>Faulconers</hi> own witnesses) that there were no such words in it, though <hi>Faulconer</hi> himself often pressed those words might pe put in, having <hi>then</hi> this <hi>design</hi> in preparation, and to put all out of doubt: besides the Testimony aforesaid, it was made apparent by the original draught of that Petition produced in Court in the face of <hi>Faulconer,</hi> all of his own hand-writing, and read in Court, and not denied by himself; and wherein there was not the least mention of the Parliament of <hi>England, or of Barbarous and Inhumane Rebels,</hi> or to be listed or entertained to serve against the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> and what stronger Testimony could there be then <hi>Faulconer</hi> against <hi>Faulconer</hi> in his own Case? all this is more then needs to be said in this business, for the Jury have found him guilty of Perjury: but only to take off that false suggestion of this unknowing Author.</p>
               <p>This Man can easily swallow <hi>Faulconers</hi> single Testimony against the Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> as ground sufficient to confiscate the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Estate, unheard, and without a Charge; but he cannot bear it, that this Infamous and Perjured Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son <hi>Faulconer,</hi> should have so much as his Credit question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a single witness, though face to face; for it is (saith he) to blemish the Judgement of Parliament, and to fill the Peoples Ears with discourses concerning <hi>Faulconer,</hi> a witness for the Commonwealth.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119472:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>